Finding Aid for Wilma T. Donahue Papers 1945-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wilma T. Donahue Papers
1945-1990
1949-1982
Donahue, Wilma T. (Wilma Thompson), 1900-
Gerontologist, faculty member at the University of Michigan, first with the Bureau of Psychological Services, later with the Institute for Human Adjustment, and as co-director of its successor unit, the Institute of Gerontology. Files detailing her participation at various meetings and conferences, her other professional activities and affiliations, research projects files, University of Michigan administrative and teaching materials, and videotapes of presentations at 1979 conference, "White House Conferences as Agents of Social Change", also photographs.
87399 Aa 2
26 linear feet in 27 boxes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The first accession of papers came from the Institute of Gerontology (donor no. 6160 ) in May 1987. Subsequent additions were received from Dr. Donahue (donor no. 7985 ) in 1991 and 1994.
The collection is open for research.
Wilma T. Donahue, born December 4, 1900, earned three degrees at the University of Michigan: her AB in 1926; an MA in 1927; and a Ph.D. in psychology in 1937. She began her career at the University of Michigan at the Bureau of Psychological Services in 1935. Beginning in 1945, Donahue worked at the Institute for Human Adjustment (IHA), where she continued to work in a variety of capacities until 1965. At the same time, she taught and carried out research on aging. By 1965 Donahue had established her position as an authority on gerontology, as reflected by her role as chair of the Division of Gerontology.
In 1965 the State of Michigan established the Institute of Gerontology, a joint venture between the University of Michigan and Wayne State University. As the co-director of the Institute in Ann Arbor, Donahue capped her long career as educator and administrator in Michigan. She retired from the University of Michigan in 1970, but continued her crusade to improve the status of the aging by serving as director of the International Center for Social Gerontology in Washington, D.C.
Donahue's career as a gerontologist spans five decades: from the late 1940s, when academics first became aware of the growing size of the aged sector of the population, to the 1980s, when the "graying of America" became an accepted feature of the social landscape. Her career was not merely academic; she took her knowledge before the legislative powers of the state and nation in her effort to secure an equitable share of social welfare for the aging. She has worked closely with government agencies and professional organizations to improve both the standard of living of older Americans and the understanding of the process of aging.
Wilma Donahue continued to be active in geriatric scholarship until her death in Ann Arbor, Michigan, in August 1993. During her long life, her interests included many facets of aging, from housing and economic security to the physical and psychological aspects inherent in the aging process. The full scope of her work can only be grasped by reading her curriculum vitae, but a sense of it can be glimpsed through the titles of some of the works she edited or wrote: Housing and the Aging (1954); Earning Opportunities for Older Workers (1955); Aging and Social Health in the U.S. and Europe (1959); Social and Psychological Aspects of Aging (1962); A Therapeutic Milieu for Geriatric Patients (1969); Adequacy of Federal Response to Housing Needs of Older Americans (1975); White House Conferences as Agents of Social Change (1979); and Aging in the 1980s and Beyond (1981).
Summary Contents List
Alumnus Place Box 26
Articles, Conferences, Addresses, and Meetings Boxes 1-14
Biography Box 26
Correspondence Box 26
Geriatric Education Box 26
International Center for Social Gerontology Boxes 23-25
Photographs Boxes 18, 19, and 27
Professional Activities and Affiliations Boxes 15-16
Research Projects Boxes 17-18
Speeches and Writings Boxes 26-27
University of Michigan: Administrative and Teaching Boxes 19-20
Videotapes (White House Conferences as Agents of Social Change) Boxes 21-22
The Wilma T. Donahue papers document her career as a teacher, researcher, and administrator at the University of Michigan. The papers span the years 1945-1990 with the bulk of the material falling within the two decades bound by 1949-1969. The Donahue papers are a subset of the Michigan Historical Collections/Institute of Gerontology Joint Archives in Gerontology and can best be understood as an integral element of that larger set.
The Donahue papers provide a clear insight to the development of the field of gerontology as an academic discipline and as an area of concern for policy makers and the general public. The earliest files reflect Donahue's training as a psychologist as it relates to her research on testing, returning veterans, and the blind. In the late 1940s Donahue and Clark Tibbitts began to research and publish articles on the aging population in America. Donahue's papers reflect this new interest as the focus of her writings now turns to issues of aging: housing, mental and physical health, adult education, and the economics of retirement. These issues dominated Donahue's research for twenty years and her papers document her increasing stature as an influential figure in gerontology at the state and national levels, especially her involvement with the University of Michigan Annual Conferences on Gerontology, the Michigan Commission on Aging, and her "cutting edge" research on housing the aging.
The collection came to the library in different accessions and from different sources. Although there is some overlap, the files as received represent distinct series. These series are Articles, Conferences, Addresses and Meetings, 1949-1970; Professional Activities and Affiliations, 1953-1970; Research Projects, 1955-1971; University of Michigan: Administration and Teaching, 1946-1968; Videotapes: White House Conferences as Agents of Social Change, 1979; International Center for Social Gerontology; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Aged.; Aging.; Donahue, Wilma T. (Wilma Thompson), 1900-; Gerontology.; International Center for Social Gerontology.; University of Michigan. Bureau of Psychological Services.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Human Adjustment.; University of Michigan. Institute of Gerontology.; White House Conferences as Agents of Social Change (1979: Latson, Va.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Aged persons--Health and welfare.; Children.; Donahue, Wilma T. (Wilma Thompson), 1900-; Dwellings--Norway.; Gerontology.; Interiors.; Psychological tests.; Norway--Dwellings.; University of Michigan. Institute of Gerontology.; White House Conferences as Agents of Social Change (1979: Latson, Va.)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Articles, Conferences, Addresses, and Meetings, 1949-1970
  Articles, Conferences, Addresses and Meetings, 1949-1970 [boxes 1-14]. Arranged chronologically regardless of type of material, this series is comprised of heterogeneous files. Correspondence, lecture notes, topical files, printed material, speeches, and rough drafts are filed by date of creation or presentation. Donahue created a new folder for each correspondent and for each time she delivered a speech; hence these files include multiple copies of addresses given at different times and places to various groups. This heterogeneity and redundancy may present problems for the researcher, but the preservation of original order (in all its diversity) gives the researcher a sense of Donahue's productivity and industry. One caveat: the bulk of the materials from 1949 to 1954 (boxes 1-3) were part of a later accession to the Institute of Gerontology archives. These are interfiled with the material processed earlier. Given the diversity of materials in this series, the best way to make sense of the materials is to refer to Donahue's curriculum vita (in the front of box 1) and to her appointment calendars (in box 14) to discern which topics might be covered in any time span.
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1949-April, 1951 (Box 1)
  - May 1951-March, 1953 (Box 2)
  - April 1953-November, 1954 (Box 3)
  - December 1954-April, 1956 (Box 4)
  - May 1956-August, 1957 (Box 5)
  - September 1957-December, 1958 (Box 6)
  - January, 1959-May 1960 (Box 7)
  - June 1960-January, 1962 (Box 8)
  - February 1962-April, 1963 (Box 9)
  - May 1963-December, 1964 (Box 10)
  - January 1965-December, 1966 (Box 11)
  - January 1967-December, 1967 (Box 12)
  - January 1968-February, 1969 (Box 13)
  - March 1969-March, 1970 (Box 14)
- Professional Activities and Affiliations, 1953-1970
  Professional Activities and Affiliations, 1953-1970 [boxes 14-16]. This series was originally organized chronologically, but has been reordered into an alphabetical series, arranged by organization or commission, to facilitate research. This series provides the best evidence of Donahue's importance and involvement at the state level in shaping public policy for the aging. The rising importance of gerontological issues in the public policy arena can be seen in the transition of the Michigan Legislative Advisory Council on the Problems of Aging to the Michigan Commission on Aging. This evolution reveals the willingness of state policy-makers (especially Governor Romney) to commit funds and institutions to dealing with the problems of aging. Donahue's responsibilities evolved in a similar manner as she came to take on more administrative roles within the institution of the Michigan Commission on Aging. Hence, these are the most revealing files in this series.
  - Appointment Calendars, 1951-1968 (Box 14)
  - Advisory Committee on Housing for the Elderly, 1956-1960 (Box 15)
  - American Psychological Association, Division 20, 1964-1967
    - Budget, Proposed, 1966 (Box 15)
    - Bylaws and Rules, 1964-1966 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 15)
    - Exhibit-Annual Meeting, Detroit, 1967 (Box 15)
  - Gerontological Research Foundation, 1956-1960 (Box 15)
  - Michigan Commission on Aging (), 1953-1970; primarily 1964-1968
    - Annual Reports, 1961-1968 (Box 15)
    - General, 1953-1960; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Grant Program Division, 1965-1970
      - Administrative, 1966-1967 (Box 15)
      - Applications: Approved (by Applicant Number), 1966-1970; 19 folders (Box 15)
      - Applications: Disapproved (by Applicant Number), 1966-1968; 6 folders (Box 15)
      - Applications: Pending, In Development (by Applicant Number), 1965-1970; 7 folders (Box 16)
      - Applications: State, 1966-1968; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Legislature, Act No. 11, 1958-1960 (Box 16)
    - Manpower Development Training Program, 1966 (Box 16)
    - Michigan State Plan, 1965 (Box 16)
    - Newsletters, 1960-1969 (Box 16)
    - News Releases, 1966-1969 (Box 16)
    - Proposals, 1964 (Box 16)
    - Publications, 1962-1966; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Survey-State Department of Welfare, 1959 (Box 16)
    - Task Force, 1964-1965; 7 folders
      - Education, 1964 (Box 16)
      - Housing, 1964-1965 (Box 16)
      - Mental Health, 1964 (Box 16)
      - Reports and Synopses, 1964-1965; 4 folders (Box 16)
    - White House Conference on Aging, 1960 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Legislative Advisory Council on Problems of Aging, 1952-1960
    - Correspondence (primarily 1956), 1952-1959; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Memos and Reports, 1954-1960; 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Minutes, 1956-1959 (Box 16)
    - Newsletters, 1957-1959 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Society of Gerontology, 1956-1969
    - Administrative and General, 1956-1969 (Box 16)
    - Newsletters, 1959-1969 (Box 16)
    - Selected Papers, 1959 (Box 16)
- Research Projects 1955-1971 (Primarily 1958-1967)
  Research Projects, 1955-1971 [boxes 17-18]. This series primarily covers Donahue's research on various nursing homes for the aging, Lurie Terrace as low-cost housing for the aging, and the work potentials of older people in medical care facilities. It is comprised of budgets, correspondence, memos, interim and final reports, grant applications, rough drafts, and tables for reports. The material is arranged alphabetically by project and research activity. Case files and preliminary reports rendered redundant by extant final reports have been removed. The Fairmount, Galesburg, Jackson, and Washtenaw projects are part of the Office of Vocational Rehabilitation study and should be viewed as complementary units. The Lurie Terrace material reflects the realization of Donahue's ideas on housing the elderly and is revealing in demonstrating her principles made real. Donahue's groundbreaking work in Milieu Therapy is documented in the Rehabilitation of Newly-Admitted Geriatric Mental Hospital Patients files.
  - Fairmount [Part of OVR Study], 1960-1961
    - General Information, 1960-1961 (Box 17)
    - Medicals (not tested), 1960 (Box 17)
    - Nursing Evaluation, 1960-1961 (Box 17)
    - Tables-Research Population, Sociometric, 1960-1961 (Box 17)
  - Galesburg [Part of OVR Study], 1960-1961
    - General Information, 1960-1961 (Box 17)
    - Medical Information, 1960-1961 (Box 17)
    - Nursing Evaluation, 1960-1961 (Box 17)
    - Tables-Research Population, Sociometric, 1960-1961 (Box 17)
  - Jackson [Part of OVR Study], 1958-1959
    - Diagnoses, 1958 (Box 17)
    - General Information, 1958-1959 (Box 17)
    - Medical Information, 1958-1959 (Box 17)
    - Nursing Evaluation, 1958-1959 (Box 17)
    - Tables-Research Population, Scattergrams, and Sociometric, 1958-1959 (Box 17)
  - Lurie Terrace, 1964-1967
    - Correspondence, 1964-1966
      - Advisory Committee, 1964 (Box 17)
      - General, 1964-1966 (Box 17)
      - Minister-Priest-Rabbi, 1963-1964 (Box 17)
      - Requests for Low Income Rent Subsidy Information, 1964-1966 (Box 17)
        see HHFA
      - Thank You Letters, 1965 (Box 17)
    - General Operations, 1964-1967
      - Advisory Committee, 1964 (Box 17)
      - Board, 1964-1965 (Box 17)
      - Budget, 1964-1967 (Box 17)
      - Draft of the Project Work, 1964 (Box 17)
      - Films and Programs, 1964-1966 (Box 17)
      - Management, 1965 (Box 17)
      - Proposal for Health Service Demonstration, 1965-1967 (Box 17)
      - Rent/Rent Subsidy, 1964-1966 (Box 17)
      - Resident Budgets, 1964-1965 (Box 17)
    - Housing and Home Finance Agency (HHFA), 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Questionnaires, 1964-1966; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Reports, "Low Income Rent Supplement Demonstration,", 1967 (Box 17)
    - Statistics, 1964-1967 (Box 17)
  - National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD), 1963-1971
    - Training Grant Applications, Peer Review, 1963-1965 (Box 17)
    - Training Grant Applications, Samples, 1965-1971
      - Birrin, USC, "Public Administration in Aging,", 1967-1971 (Box 17)
      - Bunch, Washington University, "Aging Training Review,", 1966-1967 (Box 17)
      - Donahue, University of Michigan, "Milieu Treatment of Older Mental Patients,", 1965-1968 (Box 17)
      - Eisdorfer, Duke, "Behavior and Physiology in Aging,", 1966-1967 (Box 17)
      - Forbes, Rochester, "Biological Aspects of Aging,", 1965-1967 (Box 17)
      - Loeb, Wisconsin, "Social Gerontology,", 1966-1967 (Box 17)
      - Pollack, Pennsylvania, "Social Gerontology,", 1967-1968 (Box 17)
      - Wilner, UCLA, "Gerontology,", 1965-1966 (Box 17)
    - Training Grant Applications, Summary, 1968 (Box 17)
  - Office of Vocational Rehabilitation (OVR), 1956-1961
    - Budgets and Administration, 1956-1958; 1 volumes (Box 18)
    - Papers on OVR Project, 1956-1959 (Box 18)
    - Proposal, 1955-1956 (Box 18)
    - Reports, 1956-1960; 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Visual Potential and Its Use, 1962 (Box 18)
  - Physical and Mental Activity's Effect on Functional Deterioration in Long-institutionalized, 1963-1965; 1 volumes (Box 18)
  - Rehabilitation of Newly Admitted Geriatric Mental Hospital Patients, 1962-1963
    - Monthly Reports, 1962-1963 (Box 18)
    - Ypsilanti Project: Administration, 1962-1963 (Box 18)
    - Ypsilanti Project: Report on Milieu Therapy, 1963 (Box 18)
  - Research on Aging in Michigan, 1964
    - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 18)
    - Reports, 1964; 7 folders (Box 18)
  - Special Staff on Aging, Workshop Papers, 1955-1962 (Box 18)
  - Washington [D.C.] Housing Meeting, 1959-1961 (Box 18)
    (includes photographs of Swedish Housing)
  - Washtenaw [Part of OVR Study], 1953-1961
    - "C" Group, 1953-1960 (Box 18)
    - General Information, 1958-1961 (Box 18)
    - Medical Information, 1958-1960 (Box 18)
    - Nursing Evaluation, 1966 (Box 18)
    - Tables-Research and Demonstration Populations, Sociometric, 1958-1961 (Box 18)
  - Washtenaw, Jackson, Fairmount, Galesburg Composite, 1956-1962
    - Facility Information, 1956-1958 (Box 18)
    - General Information-Research and Demonstration Populations, 1960-1961 (Box 18)
    - Manuscripts for Reports, 1957-1961 (Box 18)
    - Progress Report, 1961-1962 (Box 18)
    - Statistics, 1960-1961 (Box 18)
- University of Michigan: Administrative and Teaching, 1946-1968
  University of Michigan: Administration and Teaching, 1946-1968 [boxes 19-20]. This series is divided in two subseries. The first deals with Donahue's administrative duties and is arranged in rough chronological order. Given the extended nature of some of these duties, there is some overlap of years. The second subseries documents her teaching career from 1949 to 1960. The chronological sequence here is dictated by the semester schedule of the university. Some of the administrative materials concern Donahue's years at the Bureau of Psychological Services, but they primarily concern her career as a gerontologist. Again, Donahue's increasing responsibilities over time can be seen by comparing the Institute for Human Adjustment files with the Division of Gerontology files. The president's reports for the Institute for Human Adjustment offer her reflections on year-to-year accomplishments and goals. The manuscripts of Living through the Older Years (1949) and Aging and Mental Health (1966), both edited by Donahue, are part of these files. The Teaching subseries documents very well the early years of Donahue's career, but the materials diminish quickly in quantity and quality after 1954.
  - Administrative Materials, 1945-1968
    - Bureau of Psychological Services, 1945-1949 (Box 19)
      (include photographs)
    - Committee, Social Science Research Council, 1945-1948 (Box 19)
    - Committee to Study the Problems of the Aged in Ann Arbor, 1947-1948 (Box 19)
    - Institute for Human Adjustment, 1947-1951
      - Correspondence, 1948-1950; 5 folders (Box 19)
      - Finances, 1949-1951 (Box 19)
      - Ford Foundation Grant, 1950 (Box 19)
      - Old Age Study (Problems of Adjustment of Older People), 1947-1949 (Box 19)
      - Old Age Program Reports for Executive Committee, 1949-1951 (Box 19)
      - President's Reports, 1949-1967 (Box 19)
    - Institute on Aging Proceedings (Planning the older years), 1948-1949
      - Sketches, Letters, and Publicity, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Burgess, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Clague, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Frolich, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Kidd, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Lawton, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Overstreet, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Rabinovitz, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Stieglite, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Waterman, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Weller, 1948 (Box 19)
      - Extension Service and IRA, 1948-1949 (Box 19)
      - Proceedings and Requests, 1948-1949 (Box 19)
    - Research on Aging, 1948-1949 (Box 19)
    - Peabody Home, 1949 (Box 19)
    - Publications on Old Age (Tibbitts, Hunter, Coons), 1949-1950 (Box 19)
    - Electronic Reader for the Blind (Photographs), 1949-1951 (Box 19)
    - Research, Grants, and Proposals, 1951-1952 (Box 19)
    - Living in the Later Years, Accounts, 1956-1961 (Box 19)
    - University of Michigan Annual Conference on Aging, 1956-1961 (Box 19)
    - Division of Gerontology, Reports to Executive Committee, 1958-1962 (Box 19)
    - Grant Applications, 1958-1961 (Box 19)
    - Aging and Mental Health, 1965-1968
      - Outline, 1965-1966 (Box 19)
      - Brown, 1965 (Box 19)
      - Butler, 1965-1968 (Box 19)
      - Donahue, 1965 (Box 19)
      - Dovenmuehle, 1965 (Box 19)
      - Eisdorfer, 1966-1967 (Box 19)
      - Goldfarb, 1965-1966 (Box 19)
      - Henry, 1965-1966 (Box 19)
      - Kimmich, 1965 (Box 19)
      - Kramer, 1965-1966 (Box 19)
      - Lehman, 1966 (Box 19)
      - Lowenthal, 1965 (Box 19)
      - Neugarten, 1965 (Box 19)
      - Perrow, 1965-1966 (Box 19)
      - Portnow, 1965-1966 (Box 19)
      - Powell, 1966 (Box 19)
      - Reed, 1965 (Box 19)
      - Rosow, 1965 (Box 19)
      - Thompson, 1965-1966 (Box 19)
      - Tibbitts, 1965 (Box 19)
    - Division of Gerontology: Budgets and Accounts, 1966-1969; 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Grant Applications, 1966-1968
      - Library Service to the Aging (Casey), 1968 (Box 20)
      - Miami University, Ohio (Pilcher), 1966 (Box 20)
      - Michigan State-Oakland University (Fightmaster), 1966 (Box 20)
      - Minnesota (Vivrett), 1967 (Box 20)
      - Oregon (Scott), 1967 (Box 20)
  - Teaching and Course Materials, 1948-1960
    - "Problems of Later Maturity and Old Age, Spring 1948; 1945-1948; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - "Aging and Living,", Fall 1948; 1948-1949
      - Outline of Course, 1948 (Box 20)
      - Donahue, 1948-1949 (Box 20)
      - Tibbitts, 1948 (Box 20)
    - "Living in the Later Years,", Fall 1949; 1949-1951
      - Outline of Course, 1949 (Box 20)
      - Donahue Lecture, 1949 (Box 20)
      - Extension Service Material, 1949-1952 (Box 20)
      - Outline of Course, 1951 (Box 20)
    - Recorded Lecture Series, 1950-1951
      - Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 20)
      - Outline, 1950 (Box 20)
    - "The Care of Older People," Televised Course, 1950-1951
      - Outline and Lectures, 1950-1951 (Box 20)
      - Publicity, 1950-1951 (Box 20)
    - "Learning for Longer Living,", Spring 1951; 1951 (Box 20)
    - "Aging Blind,", Summer 1951; 1951 (Box 20)
    - "Chautagua Course,", Summer 1951; 1950-1951 (Box 20)
    - "Volunteer Service in Homes for Older People" (Workshop), 1951 (Box 20)
    - "Workshop for Nursing Home Operators, Winter 1952; 1950-1952
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1950-1951 (Box 20)
      - Outline, 1952 (Box 20)
    - "Chatauqua Course,", Summer 1952 (Box 20)
    - "Practice in Community Service,", 1952-1953 (Box 20)
    - "Delightful Things,", Winter 1953; 1953 (Box 20)
    - "General Guidance" (Workshop), 1953 (Box 20)
    - "Problems of Aging," Flint Extension Course, 1953-1954 (Box 20)
    - "Understanding Older Parents,", Winter 1954; 1953-1954 (Box 20)
    - "Understanding Your Older Folks,", Fall 1954; 1954; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - "Friendly Visitor Course,", Fall 1954; 1954 (Box 20)
    - "Counseling for Older Employees," (Workshop), 1955 (Box 20)
    - Psychology Class, Spring 1956; 1955-1956 (Box 20)
    - "Community Action for the Aging,", 1957 (Box 20)
    - Nursing Homes Educational Programs, 1959-1960 (Box 20)
    - Nursing Home Operators' Professional Training-Short Course, 1960
      - Administration, 1960 (Box 20)
      - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 20)
      - Paper by Donahue, 1960 (Box 20)
- Videotapes: White House Conferences as Agents of Social Change, 1979
  Videotapes: White House Conferences as Agents of Social Change, 1979 [boxes 21-22]. This series consists of videotapes of some of the proceedings of a May 30-June 1, 1979, conference organized by Donahue. The conference attracted some of the leading lights in the field of gerontology. Unfortunately some of the videotapes are less useful than they might have been because of uneven editing of the tapes. The Institute of Gerontology has listed the speakers and discussants at the conference sessions on videotape; these lists can be found in boxes 21 and 22.